Guide to the Colin Edwards collection on Palestine AD.MC.076
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Colin Edwards collection on Palestine
1967-1988
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Edwards, Colin, 1924-1994
AD.MC.076
2 Linear Feet in two archival document boxes, and one flat box.
Collection consists of newsletters, press releases, brochures, and other ephemeral material, from organizations based in the United States that advocated for the sovereignty and rights of the Palestinian people. These materials were collected by Colin Edwards, a Welsh-born journalist based in the San Francisco Bay Area in the 1970s and 1980s.
Conditions governing access
The collection is open for use in the Reading Room of the Archives and Special Collections department of the NYU Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate source of acquisition
Purchase, April 2020.
Arrangement
The contents of this collection were originally purchased as five different lots from the same antiquarian bookseller. Upon learning of their shared provenance and subject matter, the processing archivist decided to create an artificial collection, drawing together the ephemeral materials with the serial publications, to form one collection on the topic of Palestinian civil rights and advocacy organizations.
The collection is arranged in groups of materials by organization or title of publication, and then in largely chronological order within each group. It should also be noted that some of the newsletters contained inconsistent systems of numbering, skipping or repeating volume numbers, or in some instances omitting them altogether. In such cases, the date of publication was used as the means of arrangement.
Biographical and historical note
Colin Edwards was a Welsh-born journalist who specialized in a number of different topics, among them foreign policy and the Middle East.
Born in 1924, he spent his childhood in the town of Gorseinon, near Swansea. After finishing local schools, he attended the Royal Naval College in Greenwich, and in 1942 was conscripted into the Fleet Air Arm of the Royal Navy. After the war, he attended St. Catherine's College, Oxford, for a year, before leaving to pursue a career in journalism. Initially he covered the United Nations in New York, and from 1949 onward he worked as a correspondent embedded with British forces in Malaya, then as a war correspondent in Korea and Indochina.
By the early 1960s he had moved to the United States, settling in the San Francisco Bay area, where he began working with radio station KPFA in Berkeley, the first of a network of listener-supported, non-profit, alternative stations operated by the Pacifica Foundation. As an interviewer and producer of programs, he covered a range of topics, with most of them related to international politics, including current events in the Soviet Union, Eastern Europe, Cuba, and Northern Ireland. One area that he frequently returned to was the Middle East, with interviews and documentaries that explored the founding of the state of Israel, the Six-Day War, and the struggle of the Palestinians for self-determination, and their attempts to gain international recognition and to establish a homeland.
By the mid-1970s he had left radio to work as a free-lance writer and journalist. One of his long-standing areas of interest was the life and work of the poet Dylan Thomas. He conducted interviews with over 150 people who knew Thomas, and used these as the basis for a series of documentaries broadcast on the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation and an unpublished biography.
Edwards died on 11 July 1994, in Oakland, California.
[Source: Wikipedia article, "Colin Edwards (journalist)," https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colin_Edwards_(journalist), and website for the Pacifica Radio Archives, https://www.pacificaradioarchives.org/, both accessed on 9 April 2021.
Related materials at other repositories
Over 140 recordings of interviews conducted by Colin Edwards can be found at the Pacifica Radio Archives in North Hollywood, Calfornia, with a searchable database available at: https://www.pacificaradioarchives.org/.
A collection of materials related to his documentaries and projected biography of Dylan Thomas can be found in the Colin Edwards papers at the National Library of Wales, in Aberystwyth, along with a related collection of audio recorded interviews (https://archives.library.wales/index.php/colin-edwards-papers-2).
Content Description
The Colin Edwards collection consists of newsletters, press releases, brochures, and other ephemeral material, from organizations based in the United States that advocated for the sovereignty and rights of the Palestinian people. These materials were collected by Edwards, a Welsh-born journalist based in the San Francisco Bay Area in the 1970s and 1980s.
The collection consists of several series of publications from different organizations, including:
--League of Arab States (Cairo): this includes a small number of pamphlets, fliers, and broadsides from the League's New York-based Arab Information Bureau, as well as a larger series of press releases. The former material includes items that justify the oil embargo of 1973 as a means of drawing attention to injustices committed against the Palestinian people, a pamphlet by the historian Arnold Toynbee, and broadsides of statements published in the New York Times, including on by the philosopher Bertrand Russell. The group of news releases includes statements from League representatives based at the United Nations in New York, usually in response to actions taken against Palestinians in the Israeli-occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip.
--Palestine Congress of North America: An organization based in the United States, of members of the Palestinian diaspora who supported statehood for Palestine and the political objectives of the Palestine Liberation Organization. The monthly newsletter of this organization is represented in this collection, with 26 issues dating from 1982-1985.
--Palestine Information Office, and Palestine Research and Education Center (Washington, DC): This was a public information organization representing the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO), operating in Washington from 1978 until 1987, when the administration of Ronald Reagan declared the PLO to be a terrorist organization and Secretary of State George Shultz ordered that the PIO be shut down. The PIO published the bi-monthly magazine "Palestine Perspectives" from 1978-1982, after which it was published by the PREC. Both runs of this periodical are represented in this collection from 1978 to 1988.
--Palestinian Solidarity Committee (Albany, CA): A grass-roots organization, supporting the aims of the Palestine Liberation Organization, with chapters in Pennsylvania, New York, Colorado, and California. This collection contains 10 issues of the newsletter of the San Francisco Bay Area chapter, dating from 1976-1977.
Palestinian Arabs; Palestinian Arabs--Civil rights.; Palestinian Arabs--Periodicals.; Palestinian Arabs--United States.; Edwards, Colin, 1924-1994; League of Arab States; Palestine Information Office (Washington, D.C.); Palestine Congress of North America
- League of Arab States, 1967-1980
  - Arab Information Center: Brochure and broadside, "More in sorrow than in anger...the Arab case for oil and justice", 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arab Information Center: Brochure, "Samson shakes the pillars," by Arnold Toynbee, Undated, circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arab Information Center: various broadsides, 1970 and undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - News release: Statement by Mr. Chedli Klibi, Secretary-General of the League of Arab States on the occasion of the 32nd anniversary of the creation of the Zionist entity, undated, circa April 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - News release: Statement of H.E. Secretary General Chedli Klibi on the occasin of the 35th anniversary of the League of Arab States, March 21, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - News release: Statement by H.E. Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States at the United Nations, at the 2213rd meeting of the Security Council on the situation in the Middle East, 14 April 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - News release: Statement by Mr. Chedli Klibi, Secretary-General of the League of Arab States, on the occasion of the 32nd anniversary of the creation of the Zionist entity, Undated, circa May 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - News release: Press conference at the United Nations by H.E. Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States to the United Nations, May 6, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - News release: Luncheon address by H.E. Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States to the United Nations, at a luncheon honoring the deported mayors of Hebron and Halhul and the Muslim judge of Hebron, at the United Nations, May 19, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - News release: Remarks by H.E. Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States to the United Nations and Special Envoy to the United States, at a luncheon for the deported mayors of Hebron and Halhul and the Moslem judge of Hebron, on May 19, 1980, issued May 21, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - News release: Remarks of H.E. Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States to the United Nations, and H.E. Mr. Zehdi Labib Terzi, permanent observer of the Palestine Liberation Organization to the United Nations, at a press conference in the United Nations, 2 June 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - News release: Remarks made by H.E. Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States to the United Nations, at a press conference in the United Nations, 9 June 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - News release: Statement made by H.E. Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States to the United Nations at the 2235th meeting of the Security Council on Jerusalem, 26 June 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [News release]: Statement by H.E. Dr. Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States to the United Nations, at the emergency special session of the U.N. General Assembly on the question of Palestine, 25 July 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - [News release]: Addendum to the statement made by H.E. Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States to the United Nations, at the emergency special session of the U.N. General Assembly on the question of Palestine, 25 July 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - News release: Statement by H.E. Mr. Chedli Klibi, Secretary General of the League of Arab States on the recent resolution on Palestine adopted by the U.N. Emergency Special Session, 1 August 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - News release: Extemporaneous remarks by H.E. Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States to the United Nations, and H.E. Ambassador Salim Salim, President of the General Assembly of the United Nations, at a luncheon given by the League of Arab States on the occasion of the 11th Special Session, at the United Nations, 3 September 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - News release: Statement by H.E. Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States to the United Nations at the Eleventh Special Session of the U.N. General Assembly, 5 September 1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - News release: Text of the press conference by H.E. Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States to the United Nations, 11 September 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - News release: [Statement of Chedli Klibi, Secretary General of the League of Arab States] Tunis, 8 September 1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - News release: Text of the press conference by H.E. Ambassador Clovis Maksoud, permanent observer of the League of Arab States to the United Nations, 17 September 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous broadsides, oversized: Arab Information Center, Association of Arab-American University Graduates, 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Palestine Congress of North America, 1982-1985
  - Newsletter, Vol. 1, no. 3, September 1982 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Newsletter, Vol. 1, no. 4, October 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Newsletter, vol. 1, no. 5, November 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Newsletter, vol. 1, no. 6, December 1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newsletter, vol. 2, no. 1, January 1983 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Newsletter, vol. 2, no. 2, February 1983 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newsletter vol. 3, no. 4, April 1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Newsletter, vol. 3, no. 5, May 1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Newsletter, vol. 3, no. 6, June 1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Newsletter, vol. 3, no. 7, July 1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Newsletter, vol. 3, no. 8, August 1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Newsletter vol. 3, no. 9, September 1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Newsletter, vol. 3, no. 10, October 1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Newsletter, vol. 3, no. 11, December 1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Newsletter, vol. 4, no. 1, January 1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Newsletter, vol. 4, no. 2, February 1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Newsletter, vol. 4, no. 3, March 1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Monthly, vol. 4, no. 4, April 1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Monthly, vol. 4, no. 5, May 1984 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Monthly, vol. 4, no. 6-7, June-July 1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Monthly, vol. 4, no. 8, August 1984 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Monthly, vol. 4, no. 9, September 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Monthly, vol. 4, no. 10-11, October-November 1984 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Monthly, vol. 4, no. 12; vol. 5, no. 1, December 1984-January 1985 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Monthly, vol. 5, no. 2-3, February-March 1985 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Monthly, vol. 5, no. 10, October 1985 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Palestine Perspectives, 1978-1988
  - Vol. 1, no. 1, May 1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Vol. 1, No. 2, June 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Vol. 1, No. 5, September 1978 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Vol. 1, No. 6, October 1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Vol. 1, No. 7, November 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Vol. 1, No. 8-9, December 1978-January 1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Vol. 1, No. 10, February 1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Vol. 1, No. 11, March 1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Vol. 1, No. 12, April 1979 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Vol. 2, No. 1-2, May-June 1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Vol. 2, No. 3, July 1979 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Vol. 2, No. 4, August 1979 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Vol. 2, No. 5, September 1979 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Vol. 2, No. 6, October 1979 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Vol. 2, No. 7-8, November-December 1979 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Vol. 2, No. 9, January 1980 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Vol. 2, No. 10-11, February-March 1980 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Vol. 2, No. 12, April 1980 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Vol. 3, No. 1-2, May-June 1980 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Vol. 3, No. 3, July 1980 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Vol. 3, No. 4-5, August-September 1980 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Vol. 3, No. 6, October 1980 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Vol. 3, No. 7, November 1980 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Vol. 3, No. 9, January 1981 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Vol. 3, No. 10, February 1981 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Vol. 3, No. 11, March 1981 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Vol. 3, No. 12, April 1981 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Vol. 4, No. 1-2, May-June 1981 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Vol. 4, No. 3-4, July-August 1981 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Vol. [4], No. 5-6, September-October 1981 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Vol. [4], No. 7-8, November-December 1981 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Vol. [4], No. 9-10, January-February 1982 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Vol. [4], No. 11-12, March-April 1982 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Vol. [4], No. 13-14, May-June 1982 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - September-October 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - November-December 1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - January 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - February 1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - March 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - April 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - May 1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - June-July 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - August-September 1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - No. 10, October 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - No. 11, November 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - No. 12, December 1984-January 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - No. 13, February 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - No. 14, March 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - No. 15, April 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - No. 16, May 1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - No. 17, June-July 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - No. 18, August-September 1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - No. 19, October 1985 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - No. 20, November-December 1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - No. 21, January-February 1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - No. 22, March-April 1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - No. 23, May-June 1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - No. 24, July-August 1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - No. 27, January-February 1987 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - No. 29, May-June 1987 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - No. 30, July-August 1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - No. 32, November-December 1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - No. 33, January-February 1988 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - No. 34, March-April 1988 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Palestine Solidarity Committee Newsletter (Albany, California), 1976-1977
  - Vol. 2, No. 1, January 1976 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Vol. 2, No. 2, February 1976 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Vol. 2, No. 3, March 1976 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Vol. 2, No. 4, April 1976 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Vol. 2, No. 5, May 1976 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Vol. 2, No. 8, August 1976 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Vol. 2, No. 9, September 1, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Vol. 2, No. 10, November 1, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Vol. 3, No. 1, January 22, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Vol. 3, No. 3, May 10, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 40)